Hello it's scott manley here.
你好 我是Scott Manley
When I was a science obsessed child growing up, I learned all about plutonium.
当我作为一个迷恋科学的孩子长大时 我学到了钚的许多知识
That is the spicy rocks at the heart of atomic weapons.
它是原子武器核心中辛辣的岩石
but moreover I learned that plutonium was an artificial element
但我更了解到 钚是一种人造元素
which had been synthesized by humans in the laboratory.
它是人类在实验室里合成的
It didn't exist in nature and was entirely artificial
它不存在于自然界 并且完全是人造的
and of course as I grew up and learned more about physics
当然 随着我的成长以及对物理学的进一步了解
I learned that this was wrong because plutonium does in fact exist in nature.
我了解到那是错误的 因为实际上自然界中存在有钚
But the stuff we see in nature is generally not primordial.
但是我们在自然界看到的钚通常不是原生的
It didn't form with the earth.
它并不是与地球一起形成的
If you have any amount of uranium sitting around
如果你身边有任何数量的铀
then you will have spontaneous fissions happening in those uranium atoms.
那么 在这些铀原子中将发生自发裂变
And some of those fissions will produce neutrons.
而其中一些裂变会产生中子
Some of those neutrons can hit a uranium-238 and transform it into a plutonium-239.
其中一些中子可以击中铀-238并将其转化为钚-239
So plutonium does exist naturally in the earth
因此 钚确实会自然地存在于地球上
but because plutonium-239 has a half-life of thousands of years
但由于钚-239的半衰期仅为数千年
none of that stuff that was there when the earth was formed is still in the earth right now.
没有钚从地球形成时一直存在到现在
But there is an isotope of plutonium called plutonium-244
但是 有一种钚的同位素叫做钚-244
which might exist in the earth entirely naturally.
它可能完全自然地存在于地球上
It has a half-life of 81 million years
它的半衰期为8100万年
and that's actually pretty long for an actinide.
对于锕系元素来说 这半衰期实际上是相当长的
It's the fourth longest half-life of any actinides.
它的半衰期是所有锕系元素中第四长的
There's thorium-232, uranium-235 and uranium-238.
它前面的三个是钍-232 铀-235和铀-238
Now 100 million years or 80 million years or whatever sounds like a pretty long time
那么 1亿年或8000万年之类的 听起来是一个相当长的时间
but the earth is very old
但地球是非常古老的
and by now any plutonium-244 that was in the crust has gone through like 60 half-lives.
并且到现在 地壳中任何的钚-244都已经经历了大概60个半衰期
One estimate of how much is in there in the earth
关于在地球上有多少钚-244有一个估计
would be something like seven grams through the entire planet
估计整个地球上有7克左右的钚-244
so very hard to find any trace of it.
所以很难找到它的任何痕迹
And the thing is you can't really form plutonium-244 by accident
并且事情是这样的 你不可能真的意外地产生钚-244
by the same process of having spicy rocks sitting around in the in the crust of the earth
你不可能通过在地壳中放置辛辣岩石的同样方式来形成钚-244
because to make plutonium-244 you have to keep bombarding it with neutrons
因为要制造钚-244的话 你必须不断用中子撞击它
and as you go up towards plutonium-244, the isotopes get less stable
并且当你向钚-244的发展时 同位素变得不太稳定
and so you need to hit them very quickly
所以你需要非常迅速地击中它们
and that just doesn't happen in natural forms.
而这在自然界中是不可能发生的
It is possible to make it in a high neutron flux nuclear reactor
在有高中子通量的核反应堆中制造它是有可能
where you design it so it generates lots of neutrons very quickly
由于核反应堆的设计 它可以非常迅速地产生大量的中子
and you get that plutonium up to 244 where it's stable again.
然后你可以将钚提高到钚-244 并且在那时其再次稳定
Or it's made in nuclear weapons and you'll find that in nuclear fallout.
或者它可以由核武器制造 而且你会在核沉降物中发现它
But there haven't been any evidence that it has been found in terrestrial geology
但在陆地地质学和还没有被其探索过的地方中
and places untouched by these kind of processes until now.
还没有发现任何它存在的证据 直到现在
So there's a group uh led by a guy called Dr Anton Wallner
所以有一个由安东·沃尔纳博士领导的研究团队
and they've been looking at deep ocean sediments.
他们一直在研究深海沉积物
They're like looking at the bottom of the pacific
他们就像在观察太平洋的底部一样
and one and a half kilometers below that they've taken out cores
他们取出了在海底以下1.5公里深处的岩芯
and they've looked for extraterrestrial dust that has fallen from space.
并且他们在之中寻找从太空坠落的外星尘埃
And of course the great thing about sediments is they're laid down over time.
当然 沉积物的伟大之处在于它们是随着时间的推移而铺设的
So not only if they find these interstellar sediments or materials
因此 他们不只能发现这些星际沉积物 或着说物质
they can also correlate it with time
他们还可以将这些发现与时间联系起来
and guess what they found evidence for plutonium-244 down in these cores
而猜猜怎么着 他们在这些岩芯中发现了钚-244存在的证据
And of course the reason this is here is because this plutonium can form in space.
当然 钚之所以出现在这里 是因为这种钚可以在太空中形成
In space there's all sorts of processes that don't happen on Earth
在太空中 有各种地球上没有的过程
things like cosmic rays supernova possibly even more exotic processes
像宇宙射线 超新星 甚至可能有一些更奇特的过程
which can really throw those neutrons around.
这些过程可以真正地把这些中子抛到周围
So yeah turns out these same processes are important in making other radioisotopes
因此事实证明 这些过程在制造其他放射性同位素方面也很重要
and previously the team had been looking at iron-60.
并且在这之前 该团队一直在研究铁-60
So iron-60 is a slightly heavier version of iron.
铁-60是铁的一个稍重的版本
Iron-56 is the normal version.
铁-56是一般的版本
And it has a half-life of about 2.6 million years.
并且它的半衰期约为260万年
And that's actually way shorter than plutonium-244.
而这实际上比钚-244的半衰期短得多
But yeah back in 2015
但是 是的 早在2015年
they put a lot of effort into actually measuring the half-life of an iron-60
他们就花了很多精力来实际测量铁-60的半衰期
because this is so critical as a marker for various extraterrestrial processes.
因为它是各种地外过程关键的标志
At the time back in 2015 the half-life of iron 60
在2015年的时候 铁-60的半衰期
was thought to be between one and a half million years and 2.6 million years right
被认为是在150万年到260万年之间
so it's a huge error bar that they had to fix just by working on it.
这是一个巨大的误差 他们不得不通过研究来解决这个问题
So with that iron-60 data they were then looking at their sediments
因此 有了铁-60的数据 他们就开始研究他们有的沉积物
and they found a couple of periods in geological history
并且他们发现在地质历史上有几个时期
where they could see elevated levels of iron-60 getting deposited from interstellar grains
铁-60从星际颗粒中沉淀下来的水平升高了
so there's one period about eight million years ago
所以有一个时期大约在800万年前
where it looks like there might have been an event
看起来当时可能发生了一个事件
and then also a longer period about one and a half million years between 3.2 and 1.7 million years ago
然后还有在320万年前到170万年前间的150万年这段较长的时间
where they had a sort of continuous elevated level
在那段时间里 铁-60的沉淀水平持续上升
and one theory that was bandied around at the time and had some evidence to support it
并且在当时有一个理论被传得沸沸扬扬 而且有还一些证据来支持它
was the sun was near a star cluster
那个理论是 太阳在一个星团附近
and in star clusters all the stars form at the same time.
而在星团中 所有的恒星都是在同一时间形成的
So if you get a bunch of massive stars they all reach their retirement age
所以如果你有一堆大质量的恒星 它们都达到了退休年龄
their very violent retirement age where they go supernova at around the same time.
它们非常猛烈的退休年龄 它们会在差不多的时间里会变成超新星
So you could have a period of supernova in this cluster
所以你会在这个星团里有一段超新星的时期
throwing material sort of continuously at the earth for about one and a half million years.
在大约150万年的时间里不断向地球抛射物质
Anyway back to plutonium-244, finding this is much rarer material.
无论如何 回到钚-244的发现 发现这种物质是更为罕见的
It required all sorts of new techniques for processing the cores
它的发现需要通过各种新的技术来处理岩芯
and trying to tease out that tiny signature
并且试图从中找出那个微小的特征
but they eventually found it.
但他们最终发现了它
I mean it was a very tiny one.
我的意思是 那是一个非常微小的特征
I saw one interview with Wallner
我看过一个对沃尔纳博士的采访
where he talked about finding the six to ten atoms of extraterrestrial material in a sample
他在采访中谈到在一个样本中找到6到10个地外物质的原子
and I'm just sort of mind blown that
而且我只是觉得这很不可思议
they're able to find such a small amount of material in the sample.
他们只能够在样本中找到这么少的物质
But yeah they still have enough measurements of plutonium-244 in these cores
但是 是的 他们仍然在这些岩芯中测量出了足够量的钚-244
that they can find correlations in time.
使他们可以找到时间上的关联性
And it turns out that it's produced at roughly the same time as the iron-60
而且事实证明 它的产生时间与铁-60的产生时间大致相同
so that strongly suggests that the iron-60 and the 244 are coming from a similar source
所以这强烈地表明铁-60和钚-244的来源类似
and if that source is a supernova
而如果这个来源是一颗超新星
that would mean that supernovas can produce heavy actinide elements.
那就意味着超新星可以产生重的锕系元素
And there's a whole field of research wide open field
而且关于这个 有一整个广阔的研究领域
looking at the origin of the elements that make up the universe.
在研究构成宇宙的元素的起源
The very young universe when it forms has almost all hydrogen and helium
在宇宙刚形成还非常年轻时 宇宙有的几乎全是氢和氦
and maybe tiny amounts of lithium that were produced in a very early hot universe.
也许还有少量在非常早期的热宇宙中产生的锂
but after that it's very boring until stars form
但在那之后 就非常无聊了 直到恒星形成
and the stars in their cores they start fusing the hydrogen and the helium
而恒星在它们的核心中开始融合氢和氦
and they start making heavier and heavier elements
并开始制造越来越重的元素
and you get things like carbon oxygen silicon
所以你会得到像碳 氧 硅这样的东西
and eventually they get up to iron
并且最终它们制造了铁
and at that point they have to stop because there's no more energy available from fusion
而在这时它们必须停止 因为聚变没有更多的能量可用
and those stars that make iron their core collapses down
并且那些制造了铁的恒星 它们的核心塌陷了
and as it collapses that releases a lot of gravitational energy and blows off the exterior
当它塌陷时会释放出大量的引力势能 并将外部喷发
and it's thought that this while this is a collapse it's also an energy release
而人们认为这既是一种坍缩 同时还是一种能量的释放
which blows off material which has been transformed at the core of the star
它喷发了在恒星核心处被转化的物质
and it's not been clear
而且目前还不清楚
whether the conditions inside a supernova could make something as neutron rich and heavy as plutonium
超新星内部的条件是否能制造出像钚这样富含中子的重元素
and this is now some evidence that maybe a core collapse supernova can in fact do that
现在有一些证据表明 也许核心塌陷的超新星可以做到这一点
but the thing is like to make anything big and heavy it's not a slow process right
但问题是要制造任何大而重的东西 都不是一个缓慢的过程 对吗
there's so many when you're trying to take a an atom and make a heavier isotope
当你想把一个原子制造成更重的同位素时 有很多过程
and you're bombarding with various particles.
而且你要用各种粒子对其进行撞击
The problem is you will inevitably run into...
问题是 你将不可避免地遇到
You will hit it with a neutron
你用一个中子撞击它
and you'll make it heavier and then the heavier version is so unstable
并且这会让它变得更重 然后更重的版本是如此不稳定
it decays in with an alpha particle.
以至于它会与一个阿尔法粒子一起衰变
and you've been set back.
而这时你已经被挫败了
So there's a whole bunch of elements you can easily produce
所以 你可以很容易地制造一大堆的元素
unless you have atoms getting exposed to massive fluxes of neutrons.
除非你让原子暴露在大量的中子通量下
And it's thought that the plutoniums and the actinide elements are way up in that region.
并且人们认为 钚和锕系元素就远在这个范围之上
So another thing they did was they looked at the ratio of the iron-60 these samples to the plutonium
因此 他们做的另一件事是 他们观察了这些样品中铁-60与钚的比例
and they think that the ratio is wrong.
并且他们认为这个比例是错误的
There's too little plutonium.
因为这里面钚太少了
Now they can get estimates of what it should be in nature just by looking at things like meteorites
那么 他们可以通过观察陨石等东西和查看衰变产物的比例
and looking at the ratios of the decay products
来确定自然界中钚应有的含量
because of although the plutonium has decayed they're still trapped inside these meteorites
因为虽然钚已经衰变 但它们仍然被困在这些陨石中
or that have been sitting in space unmodified since the formation of the solar system.
或自太阳系形成以来一直存在于太空中未被转变
So you can estimate what might have been there in the past right.
所以你可以估计过去可能存在的东西 对吗
What have radioactive elements were there.
过去那里有哪些放射性元素
So if the plutonium is lower than is expected from versus this background.
因此 如果钚的值比根据这个环境预期的值低
Then maybe that indicates that supernova aren't actually the main generators of these heavy actinide elements.
那么这也许表明超新星实际上并不是这些重的锕元素的主要产生者
and that would actually make sense because we were never sure there was enough neutron flux there.
并且这实际上是有道理的 因为我们从未确定那里有足够的中子通量
And there is an alternate method for making these really heavy elements in large quantities
还有另一种方法可以大量制造这些重元素
and that is neutron star mergers
而那就是中子星的合并
where leftover neutron star cores they spiral into each other
在那种情况下 剩余的中子星核心会螺旋式地融入对方
and as they spiral in they release a lot of energy
并且当它们螺旋式融入时 它们释放出大量的能量
and this energy drives these neutrons off at relativistic speeds.
而这些能量促使这些中子以相对论性速度离开
They smash into each other.
它们互相撞击
They form a glorious cascade of new elements
它们形成了由新元素构成的壮丽瀑布
unconstrained by weak processes relatively garden-variety processes like supernova.
不受较弱过程的限制 相对像超新星这种普通的过程
The neutron star mergers are incredibly violent events
中子星合并是极为剧烈的事件
and we did find evidence for this.
而且我们确实找到了这方面的证据
The very first gravitational wave event which had an optical counterpart
第一个有光学对应体的引力波事件
is thought to be a neutron star merger
被认为是一个中子星的合并事件
and these are very likely critical in seeding the universe with these really heavy elements.
而这些很可能是向宇宙中扩散这些重元素的关键
I'm Scott Manley. Fly safe.
我是Scott Manley 切记 注意飞行安全
[Music]
[音乐]